Good morning.
早上好
It looks like 9:30 is getting earlier and earlier for everyone.
看来9点半对大家来说 越来越早了
Hello to all the people watching at home.
电视机前的家庭观众 大家好
I think there should be a requirement that
我觉得应该定一条规矩
if you're watching the video,
如果你们是在家看视频
you can only watch it 9:30-11:00 on Sunday,
那你只能够在 每周日9点半到11点这段时间看
or at least start watching then just so you can all feel our mornings.
至少在早上开始看 这样才能感受到我们早起上课的浪漫
Today, we're going to talk about balanced search trees.
今天我们讲一下平衡搜索树
Now, we've hinted at this for a while.
其实 我们之前就已经提到过了
Our goal today is to get a search tree data structure,
今天的目标是 获得一种搜索树的数据结构
so we can insert, delete, and search
可以插入、删除和搜索
all at log n time for operations.
所有操作的时间都是O(log n)
So, we want a tree that's guaranteed to be log n in height.
我们希望保证一棵树的高度是log n
So, that's a balanced search tree data structure.
那就是一个平衡搜索树的数据结构
And, we want a data structure
我们要的数据结构
that can maintain a dynamic set of n elements
它维护一个n个元素的动态集的时间
in log n time for operation.
是log n阶的
So, we'll say, using a tree of height order log n.
所以树高为O(log n)
Now, if you look very closely,
如果你细心一想
we haven't actually defined what a search tree data structure is.
我们好像从未定义过什么是搜索树的数据结构
We've defined what a binary search tree data structure is,
但我们定义过二叉搜索树的数据结构
and that's one particular kind.
而那就是其中特别的一种
And that's what we will be focusing on today.
也就是今天要具体讨论的内容
In recitation on Friday, we will look at, or you will like that,
在星期五的复习课 你会发现
balanced search trees that are not necessarily binary.
平衡搜索树不一定是二叉树
Each node can have a constant number of children, not just two.
每个结点都可能有多个子结点  不单只2个
So, I'm defining it generally.
我这个是一般的定义
You actually see what a search tree is in the general case later on.
以后会看到 在一般情况下的搜索树是怎么样的
Today, we will just be focusing on the binary case.
但今天的重点是二叉树
So, I won't define this yet.
所以这里 不会具体定义
So, there are a lot of different balanced search tree data structures.
有多种不同的平衡搜索树的数据结构
So, these are the main ones that I know of.
以下是我所知道的主要几种
The first one was AVL trees.
第一种是AVL树
This was invented in 1962.
是在1962年发明的
So, that was the beginning of fast data structures.
它是第一个快速数据结构
The next three sort of come together
下面这三种一起
and this is what you will cover in recitation this week.
会在这周的复习课讲解
So, these are non binary trees.
这三个都是非二叉树
Instead of binary, we have maybe binary and tertiary,
相对于二叉 它可能是二叉加三叉的
or maybe binary and tertiary, or quaternary,
或者二叉加三叉还有四叉
over a general concept degree, B.
或者是用一般化的概念表示：B
So, that's another way you can get balance.
这是另外一些可以构造平衡树的方法
Two-three trees, which were the second trees to be invented,
2－3树 是第二种发明的树
they were invented in 1970 by Hopcroft.
在1970年由霍普克罗夫特建立
The trees we will cover today are called red black trees.
今天要讲的树叫红黑树
These are binary search trees of guaranteed logarithmic height.
这是一种确保拥有对数阶高度的二叉搜索树
So then, there's some others.
然后  还有一些别的
So, skip lists are ones that we will cover next week.
跳跃表我们下周再介绍
It's not exactly a tree, but it's more or less a tree,
它确切来说不是树 但或多或少有树的结构
and one that you will see in your problem set this week are treaps,
还有一个在这周的练习题里会出现的 叫树堆的算法
which I won't talk too much about here.
我这里不会讲太多
But they are in some sense easier to get
但在某种程度上  它更容易构建
because they essentially just rely on the material from last Monday.
因为它的基础就是 上周一材料里的内容
So, on Monday we saw that
在周一的课上讲过
if we just randomly built a binary search tree,
如果随机建立一个二叉搜索树
it's going to have log n height most of the time in expectation.
大部分时候  树的高度都是期望中的log n
So, treaps are a way to make that dynamic,
树堆是一种使其动态化的算法
so that instead of just having a static set of n items,
而不是只有n个项的静态集
you can insert and delete into those items
你能够进行插入 删除操作
and still effectively randomly permute them
而且还能高效地打乱数组的排列
and put them in a tree.
再把它们加入到树中
So in some sense, it's the easiest.
在某种程度上 这是最容易的
It's also one of the most recent search tree data structures.
也是最新的搜索树结构之一
That was invented in 1996
它发明于1996年
by a couple of geometers, Rimon Sidell and Aragen.
发明者是几个几何学家 里蒙·锡德尔和阿拉贡
So, those are just some search tree data structures.
这是一些搜索树的数据结构
The only ones we will not cover in this class are AVL trees.
在这节课里唯一不涉及的是AVL树
They're not too hard. If you're interested,
不是特别难 如果感兴趣的话
you should read about them because they're fun.
你应该学习一下 因为会很有趣
I think they are a problem in the textbook.
我想它应该会以习题的形式 出现在课本里
OK, but today, we're going to focus on red black trees,
但今天 我们的重点是红黑树
which is a fairly simple idea, red black trees.
一个相单简洁的结构 红黑树
And, it's a particular way of guaranteeing this logarithmic height
它能保证树的高度是对数阶的
so that all the operations can be supported in log n time.
所以 它所有的操作都能在log n时间完成
So, they are binary search trees.
它们也是二叉搜索树的一种
And, they have a little bit of extra information in each node
而在每个结点  它都会附带一些额外的信息
called the color field.
称为色域
And there are several properties that a tree
而一个有色域的树
with a color field has to satisfy
还必须先满足几个性质
in order to be called a red black tree.
才能称之为红黑树
These are called the red black properties.
这些性质叫做红黑性
And, this will take a little bit of time to write down,
虽然写出来要花点时间
but it's all pretty simple.
但其实是很简单的
So once I write them down I will just say what they really mean.
我会边写边解释它的意思
There's four properties.
有四个性质
The first one's pretty simple.
第一个非常简单
Every node is either red or black,
每个结点 或者是红色 或者是黑色
hence the name of red black trees.
这也是为什么称为红黑树
So, the color field is just a single bit specifying red or black.
所以色域只需要一个位 来确定其颜色
And red nodes, I'm going to denote by a double circle
我这里会用双圆圈来代表红色结点
because I don't have colored chalk here,
因为这边没有彩色粉笔
and black nodes will be a single circle.
黑色结点是单圆圈
And you probably don't have colored pens either,
很可能你也没有彩色笔
so it will save us some grief.
所以这样表示会方便很多
Red is double circle; black is single circle.
红色是双圆圈 黑色是单圆圈
And, we sort of prefer black nodes in some sense.
所以 我们会更倾向于使用黑结点
Red nodes are a pain, as we'll see.
因为红色结点要多画一个圈
OK, second property is that the root and the leaves are all black.
第二个性质是 根结点和叶结点都是黑色的
And, I'm going to pull a little trick here.
这里要用到一个小技巧
Treat binary search trees a little bit differently
我们要稍微换个角度来看二叉搜索树
than we have in the past.
跟以前不一样
Normally, you think of the tree as a bunch of nodes.
通常情况下 树是一簇簇结点
Each node could have zero or one or two children,
每个结点有0个 1个或2个子结点
something like this.
就像这样
I'm going to imagine appending every place
我们要在附加一些东西
where a node does not have a child.
到每个没有子树的结点上
I'm going to put a little dot here,
我要在这里画一些点
an external node, which I call a leaf.
一个外部结点 叫做叶结点
So, normally leaves would have been these items.
所以 这些项一般就是叶结点
I'm just going to add to every absent child pointer a new leaf.
我们要给每一个空的子指针 添加一个新的叶结点
And, these will be my leaves.
所以  这些就是叶结点
These are really the nil pointers from each of these nodes.
它们其实是这些结点的空的子指针
So now, every internal node has exactly two children,
这样 每个内部结点都有两个子结点
and every leaf has zero children.
每个叶结点有零个子结点
OK, so these are those I'm referring to.
这些就是我提到的叶结点
These are black, and this guy is black according to rule two.
根据规则二 它们都是黑色的 还有根结点也是黑色的
Now the properties get a little bit more interesting.
接下来的性质会有趣一点
The parent of every red node is black.
每个红色结点的父结点都是黑色的
So, whenever I have a red node,
当有一个红色结点时
its parent has to be black, a single circle.
它的父结点就一定是黑色的 单圆圈
OK, so in other words, if you look at a path in the tree
换句话说 如果你观察树的任意路径
you can never have two red nodes consecutive.
你都不可能找到有两个连续的红结点
You can have, at most, red, black, red, black.
你只能找到红黑相间的情况
You can have several black nodes consecutive,
又或者是几个连续的黑结点
but never two red nodes.
但不可能是两个红结点
OK, and then one more rule.
还有一条规则
It says a little bit more about such paths.
这一条涉及到更多的路径方面的内容
So, if we take a simple path, meaning it doesn't repeat any vertices
如果选一条简单路径 也就是不重复任何结点
from a node, x, to a descended leaf of x,
从一个结点x  一直到x的子孙叶结点
all such paths to all descendant leaves
所有到各子孙叶结点的路径
have the same number of black nodes on them.
都有相等的黑结点数
So, let me draw a picture. We have some tree.
我画图解释下 有一棵树
We have some node, x, in the tree.
在树里有一个结点x
And, I'm looking at all the paths
我观察所有从x
from x down to some descendant leaf
下降到各个子孙叶结点的路径
down here at the bottom of the tree.
一直下降到树的最底层
All of these paths should have the same number of black nodes.
这些路径全都有相等的黑结点数
So, here I'll draw that each one has four black nodes,
所以 这里每条路径都有四个黑结点
the leaf, and three above it.
除了叶结点 上面有三个
We know that from property three,
根据性质三
at most, half of the nodes are red
最多只能有一半的结点是红色的
because whenever I have a red node,
因为当有一个红结点
the parent must be black.
它的父结点就一定是黑色
But I want all of these paths to have
但我想确保所有这些路径
exactly the same number of black nodes.
都有相同的黑结点数
One subtlety here is that the black height,
也就是所谓的黑高度
I didn't really leave room.  So I'll write it over here.
这边没位置写了 写到那边
This should be the same for all paths, but in particular,
所有路径的黑高度应该一致  但其实
the count I'm interested in does not include x itself.
计算x的黑高度时 并不用考虑x本身
OK, so if x is black, I'm only calling the black height.
即使x是黑色的 我也只计算下面的黑高度
So, the black height of x is this count four.
这里x的黑高度为4
And even if x is black, the black height is four.
即使x不是黑色的 黑高度也是4
So, these are just some minor details
这些只是一些微小的细节
to get all of the algorithms a bit clean.
让所有算法看起来整洁一点
So, let's look at an example of a red black tree.
先来看一个红黑树的例子
So, yeah, I'll show you an example.
对 我会举一个例子
Then I'll say why we care about these properties.
然后再讲解为什么要有这些性质
OK, so this tree has several properties.
这棵树有几个性质
The first thing is that it's a binary search tree.
首先它是一个二叉搜索树
OK, and so you can check it in order traversal.
所以你能够用中序遍历
It should give these numbers in sorted order:
来给这些数字排一下序
three, seven, eight, ten, 11, 18, 22, 26.
3，7，8，10，11，18，22，26
So, it's a valid binary search tree.
它是一个有效的二叉搜索树
We've appended these leaves with no keys in them.
我们还在后面附加了无值的叶结点
They are just hanging around.
只是摆在那里
Those are the nil pointers.
全都是空指针
So, each of these, you can call them nil.
每一个都为nil
They are all just marked there, wherever there is absent child.
它们只是附加在没有子结点的地方
And then, I've double circled some of the nodes to color them red.
有些结点画了双圆圈 表示为红色
OK, if I didn't, the black heights wouldn't match up.
如果这些节点不是红色的话  黑高度就不相等了
So, I have to be a little bit careful.
这里要小心点
From every node, we'd like to measure the number
我们来计算一下
of black nodes from that node down to any descendent leaf.
每个结点下降到子孙叶的黑结点数
So, for example, the nil pointers, their black height is zero.
比如 这个空指针 它的黑高度为0
Good. That's always the answer.
对 答案是0
So, these guys always have black height zero.
所以 叶结点的黑高度都为0
I'll just represent that here. Black height equals zero.
这里要记一下 黑高度等于0
OK, what's the black height of three?
3的黑高度是多少？
Zero? Not quite, because these nodes are black.
0？不对 因为这些点是黑色的
So the black height is one.
所以黑高度是1
You're right that we don't count three even though it's black.
对了 即使3是黑色的 我们也不考虑它
It's not included in the count. But the leaves count.
因为不用算原结点  但要算叶结点
And there's only two paths here,
这里只有两条路径
and they each have the same number of black nodes as they should.
而每一条都必然地有相同的黑结点数
Over here, let's say eight also has black height one
这边8的黑高度也是1
even though it's red.
即使它是红色的
OK: same with 11,
11也一样
same with 26. Each of them only has two paths.
26也一样 它们都只有两条路径
Each path has one black node on it.
每条路径上都有一个黑结点
Ten: what's the black height?
10的黑高度是多少？
It's still one, good, because we don't count ten.
还是1 因为不算10这个结点
There's now four paths to leaves.
它有四条到叶结点的路径
Each of them contains exactly one black node, plus the root,
每一条都包括了1个黑结点
which we don't count.
但根结点没有算进去
22: same thing, hopefully.
22应该也是一样的
This is getting a little more interesting.
但这个比较有意思
There's one path here which has one black node.
这一条路径有1个黑结点
There are other paths here, which are longer.
而这些路径更长一些
But they still only have one black node.
但仍然只有一个黑结点
So, if we just sort of ignore the red nodes,
所以 就相当于忽略这个红结点
all these paths have the same length.
所有的路径都一样长
OK: 18 should be bigger hopefully, black height of two
18的黑高度应该会大一点 等于2
because each of these paths now has one black node here,
因为这边有1个黑结点
one black node in leaves, or one black note here,
还有黑的叶结点  这边也有1个黑结点
and one black node in the leaves.
加上一个黑的叶结点
And finally, the root should have a black height of two.
最后 根结点的黑高度就会是2
It's easier to see over here, I guess.
应该很容易看出来
Each of these paths has two black nodes.
每条路径都有两个黑结点
Same over here.
这边的也一样
OK, so hopefully these properties make sense.
正如希望中那样 所有性质都成立
We didn't check all of them.
除了一个性质还没检查
Every red node has a black parent.
每个红结点都有一个黑的父结点
If you look at all of these paths,
如果你观察所有这些路径
we sort of alternate, red, black at most.
它们都是交替分布的 最多就红黑相间
Or we have just a bunch of blacks.
或者干脆都是黑的
But we never repeat two reds in a row.
但两个红结点从不重复出现
The root and the leaves are black
根结点和叶结点都是黑的
that we used pretty much by definition.
完全符合定义
Every node is red or black. OK, that's easy.
所有结点非红即黑  这很简单
This is a particular set of properties.
这是一组特殊的性质
It may seem a bit arbitrary at this point.
虽然现在看来 可能有点随意
They will make a lot more sense
一旦我们了解到它带来的影响
as we see what consequences they have.
你就会发现它很有道理
But there are a couple of goals
但这里有几个目标
that we are trying to achieve here.
我们要去达成
One is that these properties should force the tree
一是这些性质要促使树的高度...
to have logarithmic height, order log n height.
是对数阶的 O(log n)高度
And, they do, although that's probably not obvious at this point.
它们做到了  虽然在这里不是很明显
It follows mainly from all the properties.
主要是根据这些性质推出
Three and four are the main ones.
性质三和性质四是主要的部分
But you pretty much need all of them.
但实际上这四个性质缺一不可
The other desire we have from these properties is that
我们还希望 这些性质
they are somehow easy to maintain.
是相对容易保持的
OK, I can create a tree in the beginning that has this property.
在一开始  我们可以创建一个拥有这些性质的树
For example, I could make, I have to be a little bit careful,
比如说 这里要注意一下
but certainly if I take a perfectly balanced binary tree
假设建立一个完全平衡二叉树
and make all of the nodes black, it will satisfy those properties.
让所有结点都为黑色 当然能满足这些性质
OK, this is a red black tree.
这是一个红黑树
OK, so it's not too hard to make any these properties
要拥有这些性质
hold just from the beginning.
在一开始并不难
The tricky part is to maintain them.
问题在于如何保持它们
When I insert a node into this tree,
当我插入一个结点
and delete a node for this tree,
再删除树的一个结点
I want to make it not too hard.
我不想搞得太复杂
In log n time, I've got to be able to restore all these properties.
在log n的时间完成操作 之后还能恢复所有性质
OK, that will be the hardest part.
那是最难的地方
The first thing we will do is prove that these properties imply
首先 我们要证明这些性质...
that the tree has to have height order log n.
能推导出树高为O(log n)的结论
Therefore, all searches and queries
因此 这个数据结构里
on a data structure will run fast.
所有搜索和查询的速度都很快
The hard part will be to make sure these properties stay true
但难题是  即使这些性质一开始都成立
if they initially held true when we make changes to the tree.
一旦我们对树做了改动 我们要如何保证这些性质一直成立？
So, let's look at the height of a red black tree.
先讨论红黑树的高度
And from this we will start to see
从这里我们就会开始了解
where these properties come from,
这些性质是从哪里来的
why we chose these properties.
为什么选择那些性质
So, the claim is that the height of a red black tree with n keys,
有n个键的红黑树的高度
so, I'm not saying nodes here
这里不说结点
because I really only want to count the internal nodes,
因为要计算的只是内部结点
not these extra leaves that we've added,
不包括这些附加上去的叶结点
has height, at most, two times log of n plus one, so order log n.
树的高度 最多为2log(n+1) 也就是O(log n)
But, we have a pretty precise bound of a factor of two.
这有一个相当精确的因子2
There is a proof of this in the textbook by induction,
课本里有一个用归纳法的证明
and you should read that.
应该去看一下
What I'm going to give us more of a proof sketch.
而我要给出的  则是另外一种证明思路
But you should read the proof by induction
但你们应该看一下那个归纳证明
because all the practice you can get
因为归纳法能很好地帮你
with proof by induction is good.
解决实际练习中的问题
The proof sketch on the other hand gives a lot more intuition
另一种证明的思路则能让我们...
with what's going on with red black trees
对红黑树有一个更直观的理解
and connects up with recitation on Friday.
还把周五的复习课联系在了一起
So, let me tell you that instead.
那么 我来讲另一个证明
I'm going to leave that board blank and go over here.
我想把这块的黑板留空 到这边来
So, the first thing I'm going to do,
我要做的第一件事
I'm going to manipulate this tree
是对树进行改造
until it looks like something that I know.
直到它变得像是某种已知的结构
The main change I'm going to make is
我要做的主要的改变...
to merge each red node into its parent.
是将每个红结点跟它的父结点合并起来
And we know that the parent of a red node must be black.
我们知道红结点的父结点一定是黑色的
So, merge each red node into its black parent.
将每个红结点合并入黑色父结点里
So, let's look at that here.
看这里
So, I'm going to take this red node, merge it into its parent,
把这个红结点 合并到它的父结点里
take this red node, merge it into its path, and so on.
把这个红结点 跟这个父结点合并 等等
There's one up there which I can't reach.
有一个结点在上面我够不到
But I'm going to redraw this picture now.
不过我打算重新画一张图
So, seven, so the top node now becomes,
最上面的结点现在变成
in some sense, seven and 18.
7和18的某种结合
They got merged together,
它们合并在一起了
but no one else joined them.
没有别的数加入它们
Then, on the left, we have three.
然后 在左边的是3
OK, nothing joined that, and there's some leaves as usual.
没有别的数加入  和之前一样 有些叶结点
Now, if you look at, maybe, I'm going to have to draw this.
如果你看...可能还是要在那张图上画
Uh-oh. I heard that sound before.
杯具了  我又要毁黑板了
So, I'm merging these nodes together,
那么 把这些结点合并到一起
and I'm merging all of these nodes together
还有这些结点也合并到一起
because each of these red nodes merges into that black node.
因为这两个红结点都要并入这个黑结点里
And, I'm merging these two nodes together.
这两个结点也合并到一起
So, I'm putting this red node into that black node.
把这些红结点放进黑结点里
So, now you can see from the root, which is now 7/18.
从根结点看起 是7/18
There are three children hanging off.
下面有三个子结点
So, in that picture, I'd like to draw that fact
我再把结果画到另一张图里
assuming I can get this board back down. Good.
希望这块板还能多扛一会儿 好的
So, between seven and 18,
在7和18中间
I have this conglomerate node, eight, ten, 11.
有一个混合结点 8，10，11
And, there are four leaves hanging off of that node.
下面有四个叶结点
And, off to the right, after 18,
右边 在18之后
I have a conglomerate node, 22/26,
有一个混合结点 22/26
and there are three leaves hanging off of there.
它有三个叶结点
OK, kind of a weird tree
相当古怪的树
because we dealt mainly with binary trees so far,
因为到目前为止 我们接触主要是二叉树
but this is a foreshadowing of what will come on Friday.
但这算是周五内容的一个预告吧
This is something called a two-three-four tree.
这是种树叫2－3－4的树
Any guesses why it's called a two-three-four tree?
猜一下为什么叫2－3－4树？
Every node can have two, three, or four kids,
每个结点能有2个，3个或者4个子结点
yeah, except the leaves. They have zero.
除了叶结点 它没有子结点
There is another nice property
2－3－4树还隐含着...
of two-three-four trees maybe hinted at.
一个不错的性质
So, there's really no control over
首先 它是没有限制的
whether you have two children or three children or four children.
一个结点可以有2个、3个或4个子结点
But, there is another nice property.
但它还有一个不错的性质
Yeah?
问题？
[student]Inaudible
[学生]...
All of the leaves have the same depth, exactly.
没错  所有叶结点都有相同的深度
All of these guys have the same depth in the tree.
所有的叶结点在树里都有同样的深度
Why is that? Because of property four.
为什么？因为有性质4
On Friday, you will see just how to maintain that property.
在周五我们会学到 如何保持性质4
But out of this transformation,
但经过这种转换之后
we get that all the leaves have the same depth:
所有叶结点的深度都成一样的了
because their depth, now,
因为现在的深度...
or let's say their height in the tree is their black height.
或者说在树里的高度 等于它们的黑高度
And, the depth of these leaves
这些叶结点的深度
will be the black height of the root.
就是根结点的黑高度
Because we are raising all the red nodes,
因为我们把红结点都向上合并了
and we said if we look at a path,
当我们观察路径时
and we ignore all the red nodes,
把红结点都忽略掉
then the number of black nodes along a path is the same.
这样沿着路径的黑结点的就一样多了
Now we are basically just leaving all the black nodes.
而现在只剩下黑结点了
And so, along all these paths we'll have
所以 沿着所有这些路径
the same number of black nodes.
黑结点的数量都相同
And therefore, every leaf will have the same depth.
因此 所有叶结点的深度也都相同
Let me write down some of these properties.
让我把这些性质写下来
So, every internal node has between two and four children.
每个内部结点 都有2到4个子结点
And every leaf has the same depth,
而且每个叶结点的深度一致
namely, the black height of the root.
都等于根结点的黑高度
This is by property four. OK, so this is telling us a lot.
这都是根据性质4推出来的 这条性质很有内涵
So, essentially what this transformation
本质上  这种转换做的是
is doing is ignoring the red nodes.
忽略掉所有的红结点
Then, if you just focus on the black nodes,
而如果只是看黑结点的话
height equals black height.
结点高度就等于黑高度
And then, black height is telling us that
然后 黑高度又告诉我们
all the root to leaf paths have the same length.
所有从根结点到叶结点的路径都是等长的
Therefore, all these nodes are at the same level.
所以 这些结点全都在同一层
Having leaves at the same level as a good thing
叶结点全都在同一层是件好事
because it means that your tree is pretty much balanced.
因为它意味着树是非常平衡的
If you have a tree where all the nodes are branching,
如果树的所有内部结点都有分支
so, they'll have at least two children,
每个内部结点至少都有两个子结点
and all the leaves are at the same level,
而且所有的叶结点都在同一层
that's pretty balanced.
那就非常地平衡
OK, we will prove some form of that now.
现在要证明部分内容
I'm going to call the height of this tree h prime.
假设这棵树的高度为h'
The height of the original tree is h.
原树的高度是h
That's what we want to bound here.
也就是这里要限制的高度
So, the first thing is to bound h prime.
首先  我们要限制h'的高度
And then we want to relate h and h prime.
然后通过h'来求出h
OK, so the first question is
第一个问题是
how many leaves are there in this tree?
这棵树里有多少叶结点？
And, it doesn't really matter which tree I'm looking at
看哪棵树都无所谓
because I didn't really do anything to the leaves.
因为我没有对叶结点做过改动
All the leaves are black. So the leaves didn't change.
所有叶结点都是黑色的 没有发生改变
How many leaves are there in this tree,
这棵树里有多少叶结点？
and then therefore, in this tree？
这棵树也一样
Sorry? Nine. Indeed, there are nine,
多少？  9 确实是9
but I meant in general, sorry.
但我想问一般的情况...对不起
In this example there are nine.
在这个例子里是9
How many keys are there? Eight.
有多少个键？ 8个
So, in general, how do you write nine as a function of eight
在一般情况下 什么函数能把8变成9？
for large values of nine or eight?
对于9或8这种大数来说
Sorry? Plus one, good, correct answer, by guessing.
什么？加1 回答正确 猜的吧
n plus one. OK, why is it n plus one?
n+1 为什么是n+1?
Let's look at the binary tree case
我们先看一下这个二叉树的例子
where we sort of understand what's going on?
这样 我们就能明白一点了
Well, wherever you have a key,
无论哪一个键
there are two branches.
都有两个分支
And, that's not a very good argument.
嗯 这样说不太好
OK, we have what is here called a branching binary tree.
这是一个平衡二叉树
Every internal node has exactly two children.
每个内部结点都有两个子结点
And, we are counting the number of leaves
我们要用内部结点数
that you get from that process
根据这种情况
in terms of the number of internal nodes.
来计算叶结点的数量
The number of leaves in a tree, or a branching tree,
一个平衡树的叶结点数
as always one plus the number of internal nodes.
总是等于内部结点数加1
You should know that.
你应该能理解
You can prove it by induction.
你可以用归纳来证明
OK, so the number of leaves is n plus one.
所以叶结点数是n+1
It doesn't hold if you have a single child.
如果只有1个子结点那就不成立了
It holds if every internal node has a branching factor of two.
成立的前提是每个内部结点 它的分支数为2
OK, this is in either tree.
所以 两棵树的叶结点都是n+1
And now, we want to pull out some relation
现在要引用一些
between the number of leaves and the height of the tree.
叶结点数与树高度之间的关系
So, what's a good relation to use here?
这里用哪个关系比较好？
We know exactly how many leaves there are.
我们知道有多少个叶结点
That will somehow connect us to n.
它和n有关
What we care about is the height.
但我们关注的是高度
And let's look at the height of this tree.
看一下这棵树的高度
So, if I have a two-three-four tree of height h prime,
如果2-3-4树的高度为h' 那它会有多少个叶结点？
What's the minimum and maximum number of leaves it could have?
它可能的最小值、最大值又是多少？
2^h to 4^h, or h prime.
2^h到4^h  应该是h'
So, we also know in the two-three-four tree,
那么 在一个2-3-4树里
the number of leaves has to be between four to the h prime,
叶结点数小于或等于4^h
because at most I could branch four ways in each node.
因为每个结点最多有4个分支
And, it's at least two to the h prime
至少是2^h’
because I know that every node branches at least two ways. That's key.
因为每个内部结点至少有2个分支 也就是每个键
So, I only care about one of these, I think this one.
那么 我只关注这部分不等式
So, I get that two to the h prime is,
得出2^h’
at most, n plus one.
最多等于n+1
So the number of leaves is n plus one.
因为叶结点数是n+1
We know that exactly.
这是我们已知的
So, we rewrite, we take logs of both sides.
我们重写一下  两边都取对数
It says h one is at most log of n plus one.
得出h'小于或等于log(n+1)
So, we have a nice, balanced tree.
所以这是一棵漂亮的平衡树
This should be intuitive.
直觉上是这样的
If I had every node branching two ways,
如果每个结点都有2个分支
and all the leaves at the same level, that's a perfect tree.
而且所有叶结点都在同一层  那就是一棵完美的树了
It should be exactly log base two of n plus one,
正好等于以2为底的log(n+1）
and turns out not quite n.
结果比n小很多
That should be the height of the tree.
这就是这棵树的高度
Here, I might have even more branching,
我们还可能有更多的分支
which is making things even shallower in some sense.
这样  树就会变得更矮一些
So, I get more leaves out of the same height.
那在同一高度 我们就有更多的叶结点
But that's only better for me.
但这样更好
That will only decrease the height
因为随着叶结点数的增加
in terms of the number of leaves.
高度也会降低
n plus one here is the number of leaves.
这里叶结点数是n+1
So: cool. That's an easy upper bound on the height of this tree.
帅!  这是这棵树的比较宽松的上界
Now, what we really care about is the height of this tree.
但我们真正关注的是这棵树的高度 所以我们要把h和h'关联起来
Any suggestions on how we might do that?
但我们要怎么做？给个建议？
How do we know that the height of this reduced tree
我们怎么知道 这棵简化树的高度
is not too much smaller than this one.
不会比原树的高度小太多？
We know that this one is, at most, log n.
下面这棵树最多是log n
We want this to be, at most, two log n plus one.
我们想让原树的高度 不超过2log(n+1)
We know the answer. We've said the theorem. Sorry?
我们其实知道答案 因为已经讲过这定理了  嗯嗯？
[student]Inaudible
[学生]...
Right. So, property three tells us that
对  性质3告诉了我们
we can only have one red node for every black one.
每个红结点只能连着黑结点
We can, at most, alternate red and black.
所以 最多只能红黑相间
So, if we look at one of these paths
如果观察任意一条路径
that goes from a root to a leaf,
从根结点到叶结点的
the number of red nodes can be,
它所经过的红结点数
at most, half the length of the path.
最多是路径长的一半
And we take the max overall paths, that's the height of the tree.
而所有路径里最长的那条 就是树的高度
So, we know that h is, at most, two times h prime,
所以我们有  h小于等于2h'
or maybe it's easier to think of h prime is at least a half, h.
或者更容易点  h'至少是h的一半
Assuming I got that right,
这应该是正确的
because at most a half of the nodes
因为在任意从根到叶的路径上
on any root to leaf path ---- are red.
最多有一半的结点是红色的
So, at least half of them have to be black.
所以 至少有一半的结点是黑色的
And, all-black nodes are captured in this picture
这幅图只包含了所有的黑结点
cause we've thrown away the red nodes. So we have this relation,
因为红结点都已经合并了 所以我们有这条式
and therefore, h is, at most, two times log n plus one.
因此 h最多不超过2log(n+1)
OK: pretty easy.
非常简单
But you have to remember,
但你们要记住
this tree has to be balanced,
这颗树必须在平衡的情况下
and they are not too far away from each other.
两树之间的高度差才不会太大
OK, so in Friday's recitation,
在周五的复习课上
you will see how to manipulate trees with this form.
你会学习怎么改造这种树
There is a cool way to do it.
有一种不错的方法
That's two-three-four trees.
那就是2－3－4树
Today, we're going to see
今天要讲的是
how to manipulate trees in this form as red black trees.
怎么把这种形式的树改造成红黑树
And, you'll see today's lecture,
而且你会发现  今天的方法
and you'll see Friday's recitation,
和周五的复习课会讲到的方法
and they won't really seem to relate at all.
好像没有什么关系
But they're the same, just a bit hidden.
但其实它们是相同的 只是不太明显
OK, so this is good news.
这是个好消息
We now know that all red black trees are balanced.
因为我们知道所有的红黑树都是平衡的
So as long as we can make sure that
只要我们能保证
our tree stays a red black tree, we'll be OK.
我们的树总是红黑树 那就没问题
We'll be OK in the sense that the height is always log n.
从树高的角度来看 只要树的高度总是log n就行
And therefore, queries in a red black tree,
那么 红黑树的查询
so queries are things like search, find a given key,
查询跟搜索类似  都是查找一个给定的键
find the minimum, find the maximum,
查找最小值 查找最大值
find a successor, find a predecessor.
查找下一个 查找上一个
These are all queries that we know
所有的这些查询
how to support in a binary search tree.
我们都知道在二叉树里要怎么做
And we know how to do them in order height time.
我们知道如何在树高阶的时间内完成
And the height here is log n so we know that
因为树的高度为log n  所以...
all of these operations take order log n in a red black tree.
红黑树里所有这些操作 花费时间都为O(log n)
OK -- So, queries are easy.
好的 查询比较简单
We are done with queries,
这里不多加赘述
just from balance: not a surprise.
因为从平衡树出发 没什么难度
We know that balances is good.
红黑树非常平衡
The hard part for us will be to do updates.
难的部分是更新操作
And in this context, updates means insert and delete.
在这种情况下 更新就是插入和删除
In general, and a data structure, we talk about queries
通常 在数据结构里
which ask questions about the data in the structure,
查询是指访问结构里的数据
and updates which modify the data in the structure.
更新是指修改结构里的数据
And most of the time here,
在大部分情况里
we are always thinking about dynamic sets.
我们讨论的都是动态集
So, you can change the dynamics set
我们修改动态集
by adding or deleting an element.
是通过插入、删除操作
You can ask all sorts of questions.
你还可以做查询操作
In priority queues, there were other updates like delete Min.
在优先队列里 还有其它更新操作 像删除最小值
Here we have find Min, but we could then delete it.
就是先查找最小值 然后再删除它
Typically these are the operations we care about.
而这些是我们关注的典型的操作
And we'll talk about updates to include those of these,
我们会讨论更新操作 包括这两个
and queries to include all of these,
还有查询 所有的这些
or whatever happens to be relevant.
或者任何与之相关的
In problem sets especially, you'll see
尤其是在练习题里
all sorts of different queries that you can support.
你会看到各种不同的查询操作
OK, so how do we support updates?
如何进行更新呢？
Well, we have binary search tree insert,
我们有二叉搜索树插入
which we call tree insert.
也称为树插入
We have binary search tree delete, tree delete.
有二叉搜索树删除 简称树删除
They will preserve the binary search tree property,
这些操作都能保持二叉搜索树的性质
but we know they don't necessarily preserve balance.
但它们不一定维持树的平衡
We can insert a bunch of nodes.
我们不断地插入的新元素
Just keep adding new minimum elements
但它们一个比一个小
and you will get a really long path off the end.
那最后得到的路径就非常长
So, presumably, they do not preserve the red black properties
这样的话 就不能保持红黑树的性质
because we know red black implies balance.
因为红黑树必须是平衡的
In particular, they won't satisfy property one,
而且 它们还不能满足性质1
which I've erased, which is every node is red or black.
刚被我擦掉了 就是说，节点不是红色就是黑色
It'll add a node, and not assign it a color.
虽然加了结点 但没给它上色
So, we've got to assign it a color.
所以 必须为新结点指定颜色
And, as soon as we do that,
而且在上色的过程中
we'll probably violate some other property.
我们可能会破坏其它性质
And then we have to fix that property, and so on.
然后又得重新改 恶性循环了
So, it's a bit tricky, but you play around with it
有点棘手 但你要玩转它
and it's not too hard.
并不算特别难
OK, so updates must modify the tree.
要更新就必须修改树
And to preserve the red black properties,
为了保持红黑性
they're going to do it in three different kinds of modifications.
将会用到三种不同的操作
The first thing we will indeed do is just use the BST operation,
首先是应用BST的操作
tree insert or tree delete.
树插入或者树删除
That's something we know how to do.
这些已经学过
Let's just do it. We are going to
那我们就按程序走
have to change the colors of some of the nodes.
然后我们还要改变结点的颜色
In particular, the one that we insert better be colored somehow.
尤其是新插入的结点 最好先上个颜色
And in general, if we just rip out a node,
通常 如果移除一个结点
we are going to have to recolor it,
我们也必须重新着色
recolor some nearby nodes.
为周边的结点重新着色
There is one other kind of operation we're going to do.
我们还要做另外一种操作...
So, recoloring just means set to red or black.
重新着色只是改成红色或黑色
The other thing you might do is rearrange the tree,
另一个操作是对树进行重新排列
change the pointers, change the links from one node to another.
改变指针 改变从一个结点到另一个的连接
And, we're going to do that at the very structured way.
我们会用非常结构化的方法来实现
And, this is one of the main reasons that
这也是为什么..
red black trees are interesting.
红黑树会这么有趣
The kinds of changes they make are very simple,
这种改变的实现非常简单
and they also don't make very many of them.
而且不会涉及到太多结点
So, they're called rotations.
这种方法叫旋转
So, here's a rotation.
我们开始讲旋转
OK, this is a way of drawing a generic part of a tree.
这里画的是树的一部分
We have two nodes, A and B.
这样两个结点 A和B
There is some subtrees hanging off,
这里是一些子树
which we draw as triangles.
用三角形代替
We don't know how big they are.
我们不知道它多大
We know they better all have the same black height
但它们的黑高度应该是一致的
if it's a red black tree.
如果这是棵红黑树的话
But in general, it just looks like this.
一般来说 它看起来就是这样的
There is some parent, and there's some rest
当然 还有一些父结点和其它部分
of the tree out here which we don't draw.
但没有画出来
I'll give these subtrees names,
我把这些子树命名为
Greek names, alpha, beta, gamma.
希腊字母 α，β，γ
And, I'll define the operation right rotate of B.
然后 我要定义B的右旋转
So general, if I have a node, B, I look at it
一般来说 如果有一个结点 假设是B
and I want to do it right rotation,
我想要对它进行右旋转
I look at its left child and re-draw this picture
我先要对着它左边的子结点 重新把图画一遍
all the subtrees of those two nodes.
包括这两个结点的子树
And, I create this tree.
然后 得出这棵树
So, all I've done is turn this edge 90°.
我所做的 就是将这条边旋转90°
What was the parent of B is now the parent of A.
B的父结点现在成了A的父结点
A is now the new parent of B.
A变成B新的父结点
The subtrees rearrange.
子树也重新排序了
Before, they were both subtrees of,
之前 这两个都是子树
these two were subtrees of A.
都是A的子树
And, gamma was a subtree of B.
另外 γ是B的子树
Gamma is still a subtree of B,
γ还是B的子树
and alpha still is a subtree of A.
α还是A的子树
But, beta switched to being a subtree of B.
但β却变成B的子树
OK, the main thing we want to check here is that
好的 我们要确认的主要是
this operation preserves the binary search tree property.
这个操作保持了二叉搜索树的性质
Remember, the binary search tree property says that
记得二叉搜索树的性质是
all the elements in the left subtree of a node
位于结点左子树上的所有元素
are less than or equal to the node,
都小于或等于该结点的值
and all the elements in the right subtree
所有位于右子树上的元素
are greater than or equal to that value.
都大于或等于该值
So, in particular, if we take some node,
如果这里定义几个结点
little a in alpha, little b in beta, and little c in gamma,
a在α里  b在β里  c在γ里
then a is less than or equal to capital A,
那么 a就小于或等于A
is less than or equal to little b,
小于或等于b
is less than or equal to capital B,
小于或等于B
is less than or equal to little c.
小于或等于c
And, this is the condition
这种情况
both on the left side and on the right side
在左边和右边都同时成立
because Alpha is left of everything.
因为α在最左边
Beta is in between A and B,
β在A和B之间
and gamma is after B.
γ在B右边
And the same thing is true over here.
这边的情形也一样
Beta is still, it's supposed to be all the nodes
β还是...它代表所有
that come between capital A and capital B.
位于A和B之间的结点
So, this is good. We could definitely do this operation,
所以这是成立的 这个操作没有问题
still have the binary search tree,
这颗还是二叉搜索树
and we are going to use rotations in a particularly careful way
我们要用一种特别小心的方式来旋转
to make sure that we maintain all these properties.
以确保我们仍然保持这些性质
That's the hard part.
这是难点
But, rotations will be our key.
但旋转会是关键点
This was the right rotate operation.
这是右旋转操作
The reverse operation is left rotate.
反过来就是左旋转操作
So, this is left rotate of A.
这是A的左旋转
In general, of the two nodes that
一般来说 如果有两个结点
are involved, we list the top one.
我们都用上面结点来表示
So, its right rotate of B will give you this.
所以 B的右旋转会得出这个
Left rotate of A will give you this.
A的左旋转会得出那个
So, these are reversible operations, which feels good.
这都是可逆的操作 很好
The other thing is that they only take constant time operations
还有就是 它只需花费常数级的操作时间
because we are only changing a constant number of pointers.
因为指针的改变量是常数级的
As long as you know the node, B, that you are interested in
只要知道你想要的结点B
you set the left pointer of B to be,
然后把B的左指针设为...
if you want it to be beta,
如果你要的是β
so you set left of B to be right of A, and so on, and so on.
就把B的左子树设为A的右子树 以此类推
You make constant number of those changes.
进行常数次改变
You update the parents as well.
也更新了父结点
It's only a constant number of links that are changing,
只有固定几个连接被改变了
so, a constant number of assignments you need to do.
所以 只需要做固定数量的赋值运算
So, you've probably seen rotations before.
你们之前可能已经见过旋转了
But we are going to use them in a complicated way.
但这次 我们会用得更为复杂
So, let's look at how to do insertion.
先看一下怎么插入
We'll see it three times in some sense.
我们可能会分三部分来讲
First, I'll tell you the basic idea, which is pretty simple.
首先 我会告诉你基本思路 非常简单
I mentioned some of it already.
之前提到过一部分
Then, we'll do it on an example, feel it in our bones,
然后 举一个例子 从骨子里来感受它
and then we'll give the pseudocode
最后给出伪代码
so that you could go home and implement it if you wanted.
这样的话 你就可以回家实践一下
OK, this is, I should say, red black insert,
这里我应该说 红黑插入
which in the book is called RB insert,
在书里叫做RB插入
not for root beer, but for red black.
RB不是指麦根汽水 而是表示红黑
OK, so the first thing we're going to do, as I said,
正如我所说的 首先要做的是
is binary search tree, insert that node.
在二叉搜索树里 插入该结点
So, x now becomes a new leaf.
x变成一个新的叶结点
We searched for x wherever it's supposed to go.
我们先搜索x要放在哪里
We create, I shouldn't call it a leaf now.
生成...现在不应该叫叶结点
It's now a node hanging off.
应该说是一个添加到...
It's an internal node hanging off one of the original nodes.
是一个内部结点 添加到初始的某个结点下面
Maybe we added it right here.
可能添加到这里
It now gets two new leaves hanging off of it.
现在变成它下面有两个叶结点
It has no internal children.
因为它没有内部的子结点
And, we get to pick a color for it.
然后我们要给它选一种颜色
And, we will pick the color red.
选择红色
OK, why red? We definitely have to pick one of two colors.
为什么是红色？我们必须选这两种颜色之一
We could flip a coin. That might work,
抛硬币或许管用
but it's going to make our job even messier.
但这只会把事情弄得更乱
So, we are adding a new node.
我们添加的是一个新结点
It's not a root or a leaf presumably,
它不大可能是根结点或者叶结点
so we don't really need it to be black by property two.
所以根据性质2  它不一定是黑颜色
Property three, every red node has a black parent.
性质3 每个红结点有一个黑色的父结点
That might be a problem.
这可能是个问题
So, the problem is if its parent is red.
如果它的父结点是红色的 就会有问题
Then we violate property two.
那就破坏了性质2
The parent might be red, property three, sorry.
父结点可能是红色 抱歉 应该是性质3
OK, the good news is that property four is still true
但好消息是 性质4仍然成立
because property four is just counting numbers
因为性质4是计算
of black nodes down various paths.
每条路径的黑结点数
That's really the hard property to maintain.
那确实是难以保持的性质
If we just add a new red node,
如果只是添加一个新的红结点
none of the black heights change.
所有黑高度不变
None of the number of black nodes along the path changes.
沿着路径的黑结点数不变
So, this still has to hold.
所以性质4仍然成立
The only thing we can violate is property three.
唯一可能破坏的是性质3
That's reasonable.
这很正常
We know we've got to violate something at the beginning.
一开始肯定会破坏一些设定
We can't just do a binary search tree insert.
因为这不是简单的二叉树的插入
OK, so, let's give it a try on this tree.
好的 我们在这树上做一些试验
I should say how we are going to fix this.
应该说 如何弥补这个
How do we fix property three?
如何弥补性质3
We are going to move the violation of three up the tree.
我们要把性质3的破坏往上移
So, we're going to start at node x,
从结点x开始
and move up towards the root.
往根结点上移
This is via recoloring.
这要重新上色
The only thing, initially,
最开始唯一做的事
we'll do is recoloring until we get to some point
就是重新着色 直到某个点
where we can fix the violation using a rotation –
再改用旋转来弥补
——and probably also recoloring.
——很可能还要重新着色
OK, so let's see this algorithm in action.
好的 我们从例子里看一下这个算法
I want to copy this tree,
我要把这棵树重抄一遍
and you are going to have to copy it, too.
你们也应该抄下来
So, I'll just redraw it instead of modifying that diagram.
我将重新画一次 不去改变那副图
So, we have this nice red black tree.
好 我们有这颗漂亮的红黑树
And, we'll try inserting a new value of 15.
然后 我们尝试插入一个新的值15
22 is the new black. OK, that should be the same tree.
22是黑结点 好的 应该是一样的树
So now, I'm choosing the number 15 to insert,
现在我选择15做为插入的值
because that will show a fairly interesting insertion.
因为它会让这插入操作 变得相当有意思
Sometimes, the insertion doesn't take very much work.
有时 插入并不会花太大功夫
We just do the rotation and we're done.
只要旋转一下就行了
I just like to look at an interesting case.
我只是想让大家看一个有意思的例子
So, we insert 15. 15 is bigger than seven.
插入15 15大于7
It's less than 18. It's bigger than ten.
小于18 大于10
It's bigger than 11. So, 15 goes here.
大于11 所以15落在这里
So, we add a new red node of 15.
所以 我们添加了一个新的红结点15
And, it has two black leaves hanging off of it,
它下面有两个黑色叶结点
replaced one black leaf. Now we have two.
换掉一个黑色叶结点 现在变成两个
OK, now, we violate property three
现在 它违反了性质3
because we added a new red child of a red node.
因为给一个红结点 添加了一个红的子结点
So, now we have two consecutive red nodes in a root to leaf path.
现在从根到叶的一条路径上 出现了两个连续的红结点
We'd like to make this black,
如果把它设成黑色
but that would screw up the black heights
则会搞乱黑高度
because now this node would have one black node over here,
因为对于这个结点 从这出发有1个黑结点
and two black nodes down this path.
而沿着这条路 则会有2个黑结点
So, that's not good. What can we do?
所以不能直接改颜色 我们要怎么办？
Well, let's try to re-color.
那么  试一下重新着色吧
Yes. This always takes a little while to remember.
最近又变得天然呆了
So, our fix is going to be to recolor.
弥补的方法是重新上色
And, the first thing that struck me, which doesn't work,
我的第一个感觉就是 坑爹啊
cause we try to recolor around here.
因为在这周边 重新上色
It doesn't look so good
看起来没有用
because we've got red stuff out here,
因为这个是红色的
but we've got a black node over here.
而这边则是一个黑色结点
So we can't make this one red, and this one black.
所以不能让这个结点变红 这个变黑
It wouldn't quite work.
没什么作用
If we look up a little higher at the grandparent of 15 up here,
如果向上看 在15的爷爷结点这儿
we have a black node here and two red children.
有一个黑结点和两个红色子结点
That's actually pretty good news
这是非常好的消息
because we could, instead, make that two black children
因为我们能换过来 变成两个黑色子结点
and a red parent. Locally, that's going to be fine.
和一个红色父结点 这在局部是没问题的
It's not going to change any black heights
不会改变任何黑高度
because any path that went through these nodes before
因为之前任何经过这个结点的路径
will still go through the same number of black nodes.
仍然会经过相同数量的黑结点
Instead of going through a black node always here,
相对于经过这里的黑色父结点
it will go through a black node either here or here
变成了经过下面两个黑色子结点
because paths always go down to the leaves.
因为路径总是下降到叶结点
So, that's what we're going to do, recolor these guys.
这就是要做的 给这些结点重新着色
And, we will get ten, which is red.
会得到10是红色的
We'll get eight, which is black, 11 which is black,
8是黑色的 11是黑色的
and these things don't change.
这些叶结点不变
Everything else doesn't change.
其余的都不变
We are going to leave 15 red.
15是红的
It's no longer in violation.
不再有违例
15 is great because now its parent is black.
15没问题了 因为它的父结点是黑色的
We now have a new violation up here with 18
但现在 18这里又出现了一个新的违例
because 18 is also red.
因为18也是红色的
That's the only violation we have.
这是唯一的违例
In general, we'll have, at most,
通常 在任意时刻
one violation at any time until we fix it.
我们最多只有1个违例 直到弥补好一切
Then we'll have zero violations.
然后就没有违例了
OK, so, now we have a violation between ten and 18:
现在 10和18之间有一个违例
somehow always counterintuitive to me.
总觉得有些不自然
I had to look at the cheat sheet again. Really?
我必须再看一下小抄  没错吧？
No, OK, good. I was going to say,
妥妥的 继续讲课
we can't recolor anymore. Good.
不能再重新着色了
I'm not that bad. So, what we'd like to do is,
我还能再战  我们要做的
again, look at the grandparent of ten,
是再看一次10的祖父结点
which is now seven, the root of the tree.
现在是7 树的根结点
It is black, but one of its children is black.
它是黑色的 但只有一个黑色子结点
The other is red. So, we can't play the same game
另一个是红的 不能再用刚才的方法
of taking the blackness of seven,
将7的黑色
and moving it down to the two children.
转移到两个子结点上
Never mind that the root is supposed to stay black.
先不说 根结点必须是黑色的
We'll ignore that property for now.
先不说那个性质
We can't make these two black and make this one red,
我们不能让两个为黑 让这个变红
because then we'd get an imbalance.
因为这样会导致不平衡
This was already black. So now,
这个已经是黑结点了
paths going down here will have
从这边下去的路径
one fewer black node than paths going out here.
会比这条路径少一个黑结点
So, we can't just recolor seven and its children.
所以 不能将7和它的子结点重新着色
So, instead, we've got to do a rotation.
那就换种方法 进行旋转操作
We'd better be near the end.
在最后这里旋转会好一点
So, what I will do is rotate this edge.
旋转这条边
I'm going to rotate eighteen to the right.
把18旋转到右边
So that's the next operation: rotate right of 18.
所以下个操作是18的右旋转
We'll delete one more operation after this.
但这之后 我们要减少一个操作
So, we rotate right 18.
好的 我们右旋转18
So, the root stays the same: seven, three, its children.
根结点不变：7，3，它的子结点
Now, the right child of seven is no longer 18.
右边的子结点不再是18
It's now ten. 18 becomes the red child of ten.
变为10 18变成10的红色子结点
OK, we have eight over here with its two children.
8在这里 和它两个子结点
11 and 15: that subtree fits in between ten and 18.
11和15是位于10和18之间的子树
So, it goes here: 11 and 15.
移到这里：11和15
And then, there's the right subtree.
然后 是右边的子树
Everything to the right of 18,
所有在18右边的
that goes over here: 22 and 26.
移到这里：22和26
And hopefully I'm not changing any colors during that operation.
希望这过程中 我没有改变任何颜色
If I did, let me know.
如果有 告诉我
OK, it looks good. So, I still have this violation,
看起来不错 但还是有这个违例
still in trouble between ten and 18.
还是在10和18之间的麻烦
But, I've made this straighter.
但树变得更直了
OK, that's what we want to do, it turns out,
这正是我想要的
is make the connection between 18, the violator,
它让18这个违例者
and its grandparent, a straight connection:
与其祖父结点 形成一个直的连接
two rights or two lefts.
两个都在右 或者两个都在左
Here we had to zigzag right, left.
这里我们左转右转
We like to make it straight.
把树变直了
OK, it doesn't look like a much more balanced tree that this one.
但它看起来没有之前的树平衡
In fact, it looks a little worse.
实际上 变得更糟了
What we can do is now rotate these guys,
但现在我们可以旋转这几个结点
or rather, rotate this edge.
或者说 旋转这条边
I'm going to rotate seven to the left, make ten the root,
将7旋转到左边 让10变成根结点
and that things will start to look balanced.
这样看起来会更平衡
This is a rotate left of seven.
这是7的左旋转操作
And, I'm also going to do some recoloring
同时我也要重新上色
at the same time just to save me drawing one more picture
这样我可以少画一张图
because the root has to be black.
根结点必须是黑色
I'm going to make 10 black immediately.
所以10必为黑结点
I'll make seven red. That's the change.
让7变为红色 这是一个变化
And that the rest is just a rotation.
剩下的只是旋转了
So, we have 18 over here.
18在这里
I think I actually have to rotate to keep some red blackness here.
最终还是要通过旋转来保持红黑性
Eight comes between seven and ten.
8在7和10中间
So it goes here. 11 goes between ten and 18, so it goes here.
移到这里 11移到10和18之间 在这里
22 and 26 come after 18.
22和26在18后面
Now, if I'm lucky, I should satisfy all of properties that I want.
如果好运的话  这应该会满足所有的性质
Every node is red or black.
所有结点非红即黑
Every red node has a black child.
所有红结点都有一个黑色子结点
This is the last place we change.
这是我们最后改动的地方
Red nodes have black children,
红结点有黑色子结点
and all the black heights should be well defined.
所有的黑高度都很明确
For every node, the number of black nodes
对于每个结点 在到叶结点的所有路径上
along any node to leaf path is the same.
黑结点的数量都一致
And you check, that was true before,
你可以验证一下 这之前它是成立的
and I did a little bit of trickery with the recoloring here.
而这边 经过一些重新上色等小改动后
But it's still true.
它仍然成立
I mean, you can check that just locally around this rotation.
我是指 你可以在旋转的位置附近 进行验证
OK, we'll do that in a little bit.
其实一会儿 我们也会这么做
For now, it's just an example.
现在只是个例子
It's probably not terribly clear where these re-colorings
你可能不明白 这些重新上色和旋转操作...
and rotations come from necessarily, but it worked,
它们为什么可行  但它们确实有效
and it at least convinces you that it's possible.
但这至少能说服你 它是可用的
And now, we'll give a general algorithm for doing it.
现在 我要给出一个通用的算法
Any questions before we go on?
在继续讲之前 大家还有什么问题？
So, it's not exactly, I mean, just writing down
它不是绝对的 我先把算法写下来
the algorithm is not terribly intuitive.
算法不是凭直觉得来的
Red black trees of the sort of thing where you play around a bit.
像红黑树这种经常用到的算法
You say, OK, I'm going to just think about recoloring and rotations.
不能仅凭直觉 就对其进行重新上色和旋转操作
Let's restrict myself to those operations.
必须给这些操作一个严谨的约束
What could I do? Well, I'll try to recolor.
我要怎么做？ 先试着重新上色
If that works great, it pushes the problem up higher.
如果可行 问题可以继续
And, there's only log n levels, order log n levels,
树高为log n层  O(log n)层
so that's going to take order log n time.
所以要花费O(log n)的时间
At some point, I'll get stuck.
在某个步骤 可能会卡住
I can't recolor anymore.
不能再重新着色了
Then it turns out, a couple of rotations will do it.
这时做一些旋转操作就行了
Always, two rotations will suffice.
一般两次旋转就能够了
And you just play with it, and that turns out to work.
就这样重复 最后总能解决
And here's how. OK, so let's suppose we have a red black tree.
接下来就是方法...先假设有一棵红黑树
And value x, we want to insert.
要插入的值为x
Here's the algorithm.
算法如下
First, we insert it into the BST.
首先 将x插入BST
So that we know. Then, we color the node red.
然后 将新结点设为红色
And here, I'm going to use a slightly more precise notation.
这里要用到一个 略微精确的定义
Color is a field of x.
颜色是x的一个域
And now, we are going to walk our way up the tree
然后我们要一直往上走
with a while loop until we get to the root,
用一个循环的算法 直到根结点为止
or until we reach a black node.
或者x变为一个黑结点
So, in general, x initially is
一般来说 x一开始代表着...
going to be the element that we inserted.
要插入的元素
But, we're going to move x up the tree.
但我们要把x往上移
If ever we find that x is a black node,
如果发现x是一个黑结点
we're happy because maybe its parent is red.
我们会很满意 因为它的父结点可能是红色
Maybe it isn't. I don't care.
也可能不是 但无所谓
Black nodes can have arbitrarily colored parents.
黑结点可以拥有任意颜色的父结点
It's red nodes that we worry about.
我们担心的只是红结点的情况
So, if x is red, we have to keep doing this loop.
如果x是红色 那继续这个循环算法
Of course, I just wrote the wrong one.
当然 这里写错了
While the color is red, we're going to keep doing this.
当颜色为红色时 就不断地循环
So, there are three cases, or six,
所以这里分3种情况 或者6种
depending on how you count.
这要看你怎么算
That's what makes this a little bit tricky to memorize.
这是一个记忆的小技巧
OK, but there are some symmetric situations.
因为也有一些对称的情况
Let me draw them. What we care about, I've argued,
让我把它画下来 我们所讨论的是
is between x and its grandparent.
是x和它祖父结点之间的部分
So, I'm using p of x here to denote
这里用p[x]来表示
parent of x just because it's shorter.
x的父结点 这样更简洁
So, p of x is x's grandparent.
所以p[p[x]]表示x的祖父结点
Left of p of x is the left child.
left[p[p[x]]]就是左子结点
So, what I'm interested in is I look at x.
我们关注的是x
And, if I don't assign any directions, x is the child of some p of x,
如果我不画箭头 x是p[x]的子结点
and p of x is the child of the grandparent, p of p of x.
p[x]是祖父结点p[p[x]]的子结点
Now, these edges aren't vertical.
实际上 这些关系线不是垂直的
They are either left or right.
或者是左 或者是右
And, I care about which one.
但我关注的是...
In particular, I'm looking at whether the parent is
我想知道 父结点是不是
the left child of the grandparent.
祖父结点的左子结点
So, I want to know, does it look like this?
我想知道 它是不是这个样子的？
OK, and I don't know whether x is
我不知道x是它父结点的
to the left or to the right of the parent.
左子结点还是右子结点
But, is parent of x the left child of p of p of x,
但x的父结点是p[p[x]]的左子结点
or is it the right child?
还是它的右子结点？
And these two cases are totally symmetric.
这两种情况完全对称
But I need to assume it's one way or the other.
但我要假设是其中的一种
Otherwise, I can't draw the pictures.
否则我画不了图
OK, so this will be, let's call it category A.
假设是这样 我们称之为A类
And, this is category B.
这是B类
And, I'm going to tell you what to do in category A.
我会告诉你在A类的情况下要怎么做
And category B is symmetric. You just flip left and right.
B类是对称的 只需要左换成右
OK, so this is A.
这是A类
So, within category A, there are three cases.
在A类里还分三种情况
And within category B,
在B类里
there is the same three cases, just reversed.
也有三种同样的情况 只是反过来了
So, we're going to do is look at the other child of the grandparent.
我们要做的是查看祖父结点的另一个子结点
This is one reason why we sort of
这也是为什么我们要知道
need to know which way we are looking.
它属于哪一种情况的原因
If the parent of x is the left child of the grandparent,
如果x的父结点是祖父结点的左子结点
we're going to look at the other child of the grandparent,
那我们就看一下祖父的另外一个子结点
which would be the right child of the grandparent, call that node y.
也就是祖父的右子结点 设该结点为y
This is also known as the uncle or the aunt of x,
也可以看成是x的大叔结点或大婶结点
depending on whether y is male or female.
这要看y是男还是女
OK, so this is uncle or aunt.
好的 这是大叔或大婶
Unfortunately, in English,
不幸的是 在英语里
there is no gender-free version of this as far as I know.
就我所知 还没有无性别的版本
There's parent and child, but no uncle-aunt.
有家长结点和子结点 但没有叔婶结点
I'm sure we could come up with one.
我们肯定能想到一个
I'm not going to try. It's going to sound bad.
但我不打算尝试 因为一定很坑爹
OK, so why do I care about y?
为什么我这么在乎y呢？
Because, I want to see if I can do this recoloring step.
因为我想知道 能不能做重新上色这个步骤
The recoloring idea was, well,
重新上色的思路是...
the grandparents, let's say it's black.
假设祖父结点是黑色
If I can push the blackness of the grandparent
如果我能将祖父结点的黑色
down into the two children,
向下转移给两个子结点
then if both of these are red, in other words, then I'd be happy.
换个角度 如果两个子结点都是红色的 那就解决了
Then I'd push the problem up.
那我就能把问题往上移
This guy is now red. This guy is black.
p[p[x]]变为红色  p[x]变成黑结点
So these two are all right.
这两个都没问题了
This one may violate the great grandparent.
这虽然可能与曾祖父结点冲突
But we will just keep going up, and that will be fine.
但我们继续向上执行这个步骤 那就没问题
Today, if we're lucky, y is red.
如果运气好的话 y是红的
Then we can just do recoloring.
然后直接重新上色
So, if the color of y is red, then we will recolor.
如果y是红色 则重新上色
And, I'm going to defer this to a picture called case one.
我会把它归入情形一的图里
OK, let me first tell you how the cases breakup,
好的 我先说一下分别是哪几种情形
and then we will see how they work.
再分别看一下它们如何运作
So, if we're not in case one,
如果不是情形一
so this else should be aligned with that,
这个else应该和上面对齐
then, then we are either in case two or three.
那就会是情形二或情形三
So, here's the dichotomy.
这又分为两种情形
It turns out we've actually seen all of the cases,
实际上我们见过所有的情形
maybe not A versus B, but we've seen the case
也许不是A相对于B 但在最开始
of the very beginning where we just recolor.
我们讲重新上色的时候 见过这种情形
That's case one. The next thing we saw is,
那是情形一 而第二种情形则是...
well, it's kind of annoying that the grandparent and ten,
那个蛋疼的祖父结点和10...
so seven and ten were not straight.
就是7和10的不在直线上
They were zigzagged.
是Z形的
So, case two is when they are zigzagged.
情形二是当它们为Z形时
It turns out if x is the right child of its parent,
如果x是父结点的右子结点
and the parent is the left child of the grandparent,
而父结点 又是祖父结点的左子结点
that's a we've assumed so far, that is case two.
这就是目前所假设的情形二
OK, the other case is that x is the left child of its parent.
另一种情形是 x是父结点的左子结点
So, then we have a left chain,
那么左边就成链状
x, parent of x, grandparent of x.
x  x的父结点  x的祖父结点
That is case three.
这就是情形三
OK, I did not write else here
这里没有写“其它”
because what case two does is it reduces to case three.
因为情形三是由情形二简化得出的
So, in case two, we are going to do the stuff that's here.
所以在情形二 我们要做这些额外操作
And then, we're going to do the stuff here.
然后 是下面的操作
For case three, we just do the stuff here.
如果是情形三 只需要做这些操作
Or in case one, we just do the stuff here.
在情形一 只要做这些操作
And then, that finishes the three cases on the A side,
然后 这就完成了A类的三种情形
then back to this if. We say else, this is case B,
回到这个if  这个else指的是B类
which is the same as A,
和A类一样
but reversing the notions of left and right,
但左右是互换的
OK, in the natural way.
非常自然
Every time we write left of something,
每次提到的“左”
we instead write right of something, and vice versa.
都换成“右” 或者反过来
So, this is really just flipping everything over.
只需要将所有左右翻转
We'll just focus on category A.
我们只把A类作为重点
And, let's see what we do in each of the three cases.
看一下这三种情形分别 该如何处理
We've seen it in an example.
我们已经在一个例子里看过了
But let's do it generically. Let's do it here.
但更一般化的算法 我们写在这儿
Sorry, there's one more line to the algorithm, I should say.
不好意思 这个算法还有一步
It's not aligned with here. We color the root.
不是跟这里对齐的 这一步是给根结点上色
There's a chance when you do all of this
所有这些操作 都有可能
that the root becomes red.
让根结点变为红色
We always want the root to be black.
我们想要根结点总为黑色
If it's red, we set it to black at the very end of the algorithm.
如果它为红 则在算法最后将它设为黑色
This does not change the black height property.
这个并不影响黑高度的性质
Everything will still be fine because every path
所有性质都依然成立 因为每条路径...
either goes to the root or it doesn't, every x to leaf path.
要么都经过根结点 要么都不经过 每条x到叶的路径
So, changing the root from red to black is no problem.
所以 把根结点从红色变为黑色是没有问题的
It will increase the black heights of everyone,
虽然会增加每条路径的黑高度
but all the paths will still have the same value.
但所有路径的黑高度仍保持一致
It will be one larger.
全部都加1
So, let's look at the three cases.
回到这三种情形
And, I'm going to use some notation.
我还要用一些定义
Remember, we had triangles in order to
还记得吗 当我们定义旋转时
denote arbitrary subtrees when we define a rotation.
我们用三角形来表示任意一个子树
I'm going to use triangle with a dot on top
我们用一个顶角带点的三角形
to say that this subtree has a black root.
来表示有黑色根结点的子树
So, when I fill something white, it means black
虽然填充的是白色 但实际上它是黑结点
because I'm on a black board.
因为它是写在黑板上
Sorry. OK, and I also have the property that
好的  同时它还有一个性质
each of these triangles have the same black height.
每个三角形的黑高度一致
So, this will let me make sure that
这样能确保
the black height property, property four, is being observed.
黑高度性质 就是性质4能被观察得到
So, let me just show you case one.
讲一下情形一
We always want to make sure property four is preserved
我们总要保证性质4不被破坏
because it's really hard to get that back.
因为如果破坏了就很难改回来
It's essentially the balance of the tree.
它代表的是树的平衡性
So, let's suppose we have some node,
假设有一些结点
C, left child, A, right child, B,
C结点 左子结点A 右子结点B
and some subtrees hanging off of those guys.
还有其下的一些子树
And, all of those subtrees have the same black height.
所有子树都有相同的黑高度
So, in other words, these things are all at the same level.
换句话说 它们都在同一层
OK, this is not quite what I wanted,
好吧 这不是我想要的
sorry. So, I'm considering, this is node x.
抱歉了 假设这是x结点
x is red, and its parent is red.
x是红色 而且它的父结点为红
Therefore, we need to fix something.
因此 需要改变某些结构
We look at the node, y, which is over here.
看一下另一边的结点y
And, I'll call it, the key is D.
假设里面的键值是D
The node is called y. OK, it has subtrees hanging off as well,
这个结点称为y 同样也有一些子树
all with the same black height.
都有相同的黑高度
So, that will be true. If all of these nodes are red,
如果所有这些结点都是红的
then all of these nodes have the same black height.
则所有这些结点都有相同的黑高度
And therefore, all of the child subtrees,
因此 所有这些
which have black roots,
有黑色根结点的子树
all had to have the same black height as well.
同样也有相同的黑高度
OK, so we're looking at a big chunk of red children subtree of a black node
把这看成是拥有大量红色子结点的黑结点
looking at all the stuff that happens to be red.
它的所有子结点恰好都是红色的
In case one, why is red so it participates?
在情形一里 因为红色是可以被合并的
So, a way to think of this as if we converted
如果转换成2－3－4树
into the two-three-four-tree, or tried to,
或者试着转换
we would merge all of this stuff into one node.
这里所有红结点 都会合并到这一个结点里
That's essentially what we're doing here.
这就是所要做的
This is not a two-three-four tree, though.
尽管这个不是2－3－4树
We now have five children, which is bad.
因为它有5个子结点 相当糟糕
This is why we want to fix it.
这也是要做弥补的原因
So, we're going to recolor in case one.
情形一需要重新着色
And, we're going to take C.
取结点C
Instead of making C black, and A and D red,
我们不是要把C设为黑 让A和D为红
we are going to make A and D black, and C red.
而是把A和D设为黑 C设为红
So, C is red. A is black. D is black.
这样 C是红色 A是黑色 D是黑色
And, the subtrees are the same.
子树不变
B is the same. It's still red.
B也不变 还是红色
OK, now we need to check that we preserve property four,
接下来 要检查这颗树是否仍保持性质4
that all of the paths have the same number of black nodes.
是不是所有路径的黑结点数一致
That follows because we know we didn't touch these subtrees.
这是成立的 因为所有子树都没有改动
They all have the same black height.
仍然有着相同的黑高度
And, if you look at any path, like,
如果你观察任意一条路径 例如
all the paths from A are going to have that black height.
所有从A出发的路径 都有这个黑高度
All the paths from C are going to have that black height plus one
所有从C出发的路径 都是这个黑高度加1
because there's a black node in all the left paths,
因为在所有左边的路径上 都多了个黑结点
and there is a black node in all the right paths.
在所有右边的路径上 也都多了个黑结点
So, all the black links are the same.
因此 所有黑结点数相等
So, this preserves property four.
所以它保持着性质4
And, it fixes property three locally
而且 它也把这一块的性质3给改好了
because B used to violate A.
因为B之前跟A是冲突的
Now B does not violate anything.
现在B没有违反任何东西
C, now, might be violated.
C反而可能是违例
So, what we're going to do is set x,
所以 我们要把x指向...
our new value of x, will be C.
新的x的值 将指向C
So, it used to be B. We move it up a couple levels.
之前x的值是B 现在向上移了几层
Or, in the original tree, yeah,
同样 在原来的树里
we also move it up a couple levels.
x也向上移了几层
So, we're making progress up the tree.
就这样向上不断修正这棵树
And then we continue this loop.
然后继续这个循环
That's case one: recolor, go up.
这是情形一：重新上色 向上查找
C may violate its parent in which case we have to recurse.
C可能会与它的父结点冲突 但这必须用递归来解决
So, we are recursing, in some sense, or continuing on C.
应该说 我们是在递归 或者是从C继续循环
So now, let's look at case two.
现在看一下情形二
So, I'm still, in some sense, defining this algorithm by picture.
那我继续通过图 来说明这个算法
This is some nice, graphical, programming language.
这真是个不错的、"可视化"的编程语言
So, let's draw case two.
我们来画一下情形二
Yeah, I forgot to mention something about case one.
我忘了说情形一的某个内容了
So, I drew some things here.
那么 我在这里画了一些图
What do I actually know is true?
但我最后得出的什么？
So, let's look at the algorithm in which I've now reversed.
我们再看一下 那个相反的算法
We are assuming that we are in category A.
我们假设 现在是A类的情况
In other words, the parent is the left child of the grandparent.
换句话说 父结点是祖父结点的左子结点
So, A is the left child of C. That much I knew.
也就是说 已知A是C的左子结点
Therefore, y is the right child.
因此 y是右子结点
D is the right child of C.
D是C的右子结点
I didn't actually know
实际上 我并不知道
whether B was the right child or the left child.
B到底是右子结点 还是左子结点
It didn't matter. In case one, it doesn't matter.
关系不大 在情形一里并不影响
OK, so I should've said, the children of A may be reversed.
虽然A的子结点可能在反方向上
But it just said the same picture.
但实际上都一样
OK, I thought of this because in case two, we care.
我之所以说这个 是因为情形二里它是有影响的
So, case one: we didn't really care.
在情形一里 我们不用关注这个
In case two, we say, well, case two is up there,
但在情形二里 我们就要关注...情形二在上面
is x the right child of the parent, or the left child?
x是右子结点还是左子结点？
If it's the right child, we are in case two.
如果它是右子结点 那就是情形二
So now, I can really know that x here,
那这里 我们已知x是在这里
which is B, is the right child of A.
也就是B——A的右子结点
Before, I didn't know and I didn't care.
情形一里 我既不清楚也不在乎
Now, I'm assuming that it's this way.
现在 我们假设它是这种情况
OK, y is still over here.
y还是在另一边
And now, now we know that y is black.
而且 已知y是黑色的
So, y over here is a black node.
所以 这里的y是一个黑结点
So now, if I did the contraction trick,
现在 如果我用合并的技巧
all of these nodes, A, B, and C, would conglomerate into one.
把所有这些结点：A，B，C合并到一起
I only have four children. That actually looks pretty good.
那我就只有四个子结点 看起来非常不错
y would not be involved because it's black.
y不参与合并 因为它是黑结点
So, in this case, we are going to do a left rotation on A.
在这种情况下 我们对A进行左旋转
So, we take the edge, we turn at 90°.
取这条边 旋转90°
What we get is A on the left, B on the right still.
结果是A还在左边 B还在右边
It should preserve the in order traversal, C up top still.
这还保持中序遍历的性质 C还在上面
We have the y subtree hanging off, as before.
y子树跟之前一样还是在这
We have one of the other three subtrees hanging off B,
其它三棵子树中 有一棵到了B下面
and the other two now hang off A.
还有其它两棵在A下面
So, this is just a generic rotation picture applied to this edge.
这是对这条边旋转得到的一个的图
OK, what that does, is before we had a zigzag
使用前 x与它的祖父结点之间
between x and its grandparent. Now, we have a zigzig.
是一个Z形关系 现在曲线变直线了
We have a straight path between x.
有一个笔直的路径穿过x
So, x is still down here. I'm not changing x in this case
x还是在下面 这种情况下我们不改变x
because after I do case two, I immediately do case three.
因为在情形二之后 马上就进入情形三
So, this is what case three will look like.
这就是情形三的样子
And now, I continue on to case three.
接下来讲到情形三
So, finally, here's case three.
终于 我们讲到了情形三
And, this will finally complete the insertion algorithm.
我们也终于要完成这个插入算法
We have a black node, C. We have a red left child from C.
有一个黑结点C 它有一个红色左子结点
We have a red, left, grandchild which is x.
有一个红色左子孙结点x
And then, we have these black subtrees
还有这些黑色子树
all of the same black height hanging off, OK,
它们的黑高度都一致
which is exactly what we had at the end of case two.
这和情形二在最后的图完全一样
So, that definitely connects over.
照本复制过来
And remember, this is the only case left in category A.
记住 这是A类里剩下的最后一种情形
Category A, we assumed that B was the parent of x,
在A类里 我们假设B是x的父结点
was the left child of the grandparent, here C.
也是祖父结点的左子结点 这个C
So, we know that.
这些都是已知的
We already did the case one, y over here as red.
我们已经讲过情形一了 y是红色的
That was case one. So, we are assuming y is black.
那是情形一 所以这里假设y是黑色的
Now, we look at whether x was the left child or the right child.
现在我们就要看  x是左子还是右子
If it was the right child, we made it into the left child.
如果是右子结点  则将它转成左子结点
x actually did change here. Before, x was B.
x在这里确实有变化的 之前x是B
Now, x is A. OK, and then case three, finally,
现在x是A  好的 最后就是情形三了
is when x is the left child of the parent
就是x是左子结点
who is the left child of the grandparent.
而它的父结点也是左子结点时
This is the last case we have to worry about.
这是最后要考虑的情形
And, what we do is another rotation just like
我们要做的 是另一次旋转
the last rotation we did in the example.
就像上次在例子里做的旋转一样
That was case three.
这就是情形三
So, we're going to do a right rotate in this case of C.
在这种情况下 我们要对C进行右旋转
And, we are going to recolor.
而且要重新上色
OK, so, what do we get?
好的 我们会得到什么呢？
Well, B now becomes the root.
那么  B现在变成根结点
And, I'm going to make it black.
我们要把它设为黑色
OK, remember, this is the root of the subtree.
要记住 这也只是子树的根结点
There is other stuff hanging off here.
图外面还有树的其它部分
I really should have drawn extra parents
在所有这些图里 其实应该
in all of these pictures.
还有更多的父结点
There was somewhere in the middle of the tree.
这只是一棵树的某个部分
I don't know where. It could be a rightward branch;
我不知道是哪部分 可能是一个向右的分支
it could be a leftward branch. We don't know.
也可能是一个向左的分支 我不知道
C becomes the child of B, and I'm going to make it a red child.
C变成B的子结点 将它设为红色子结点
A becomes a child of B, as it was before, keep it red.
A变成B的子结点 跟之前一样保持红色
And, everything else just hangs off.
其它挂着部分保持不变
So, there were four subtrees all at the same black height.
这里有四棵黑高度相等的子树
And, in particular, this last one had y,
特别是最后一棵 拥有结点y
but we don't particularly care about y anymore.
但我们不再特别地关注y了
Now, we are in really good shape
现在看起来 树的形状已经很不错了
because we should have no more violations.
因为再也没有冲突了
Before, we had a violation between x and its parent, A and B.
之前发生冲突的是 x和它的父结点——A和B
Well, A and B still have a parent child relation.
A和B仍然是父子结点的关系
But B is now black. And, B is black,
但B现在是黑色的
so we don't care what its parent looks like.
先不管B的父结点是什么颜色
It could be red or black. Both are fine.
是红是黑 都没问题
We are no longer violating property three.
这幅图已经不再违反性质三
We should be done in this case.
这里已经完事了
Property three is now true.
性质三是成立的
If you want, you can say, well, x becomes this node.
你可以这样想 x变成这个结点
And then, the loop says, oh, x is no longer red.
在检查循环条件时  x不再是红色
Therefore, I'm done. We also need to check that
因此 循环结束  但同时 我们还要检查
property four is preserved during this process.
在这个过程中性质4是否还保持着
Again, it's not hard
同样 这不难
because of the two-three-four tree transformation.
因为有2－3－4树转换
If I contract all the red things into their parents,
如果将所有红结点合并到它们的父结点里
everything else has a constant, I mean,
其它都是一个常值了  我的意思是
every path in that tree has the same length
树里的每条路径都有相同的长度
because they have the same black length.
因为它们有相等的黑高度
And over here, that will still be true.
在这边 同样成立
It's a little bit trickier here,
这里抄了点近路
because we are recoloring at the same time.
因为我们在旋转的同时 也重新上色了
But, if you look at a path that comes through this tree,
但是如果你观察这棵树的任意路径
it used to go through a black node, C,
在这图里 它们都会经过黑结点C
and then maybe some red stuff; I don't care.
还有一些红结点之类的  但那些不用管
And then, it went through these trees,
然后是这些子树
which all have the same black height.
因为它们黑高度相同
So they were all the same.
所以所有路径的黑高度也一致
Now, you comment, and you go through a black node called B.
现在 路径经过一个黑结点B
And then, you go through some red nodes.
然后是一些红结点
It doesn't really matter. But all the trees that you go through
那不影响  但再往下的所有子树
down here have the same black height.
黑高度都相同
So, every path through this tree
所以 经过这棵树的每条路径
will have the same black length, OK,
都有相同的黑高度
if it starts from the same node.
当然 它们是从同一个结点出发
So, we preserve property four. We fix property three.
这样我们保持了性质4 弥补了性质3
That is the insertion algorithm. It's pretty long.
这就是插入算法 一匹布那么长
This is something you'll probably just have to memorize.
这些东西 你可能必须记下来
If you try a few examples, it's not so hard.
但如果你实践过一些例子 就知道它并不太难
We can see that all the things we did
在这个例子里 我们所做的
in this example were the three cases.
无非都是这三种情形
The first step, which unfortunately I had to erase for space,
第一步...很遗憾 因为要腾空间 我擦掉了
all we did was recolor.
我们所做的是重新上色
We recolored ten, and eight, and 11.
把10，8  还有11重新上色
That was a case one.
这是情形一
Ten was the grandparent of 15.
10是15的祖父结点
Then, we looked at ten. Ten was the violator.
然后 我们看到10  10发生冲突了
It was a zigzag case relative to its grandparent.
而且 它和祖父结点之间是Z形关系
So, we did a right rotation to fix that, took this edge,
所以 我们对这条边做右旋转来补救
and turned it so that ten became next to seven.
将它转过来 这样10变成紧挨着7
That's the picture on the top.
变成上面那张图
Then, 18, which is the new violator,
18是新的违例者
with its grandparent, is a zigzig.
它和祖父结点是直线关系
They are both going in the same direction.
它们都在同一边
And, now, we do one more rotation to fix that.
然后 我们再做一次旋转来补救
That's really the only thing you have to remember.
这是唯一要记住的地方
Recolor your grandparent if you can.
如果可以的话 将祖父结点重新着色
Otherwise, make it zigzig.
否则 将它变为直线关系
And then, do one last rotation.
然后 做最后一次旋转
And recolor. And that will work.
并且重新上色 那就可以了
I mean, if you remember that,
如果你把这些都记下来了
you will figure out the rest on any particular example.
你就能应付任意一个例子
We rotate ten over. That better be black,
我们把10旋转过去 把它变成黑结点
because in this case it's becoming the root.
因为在这里 它会变为根结点
But, we will make it black no matter what happens
但无论如何 我们都会将它设为黑色
because there has to be one black node there.
因为根节点必须为黑色
If we didn't recolor at the same time,
如果没有同步进行重新上色
we would violate property four.
就会违反性质4
Why don't I draw that just for,
人家才不会把这种情况画下来呢
OK, because I have a couple minutes.
好吧 看在还有几分钟时间
So, if we just did the rotation here,
如果这里只做旋转操作
so let's say, not the following, we take B. B is red.
先写好 这不是推论  取B为红色
This will give some intuition
这么做能直观地告诉我们
as to why the algorithm is this way, and not some other way.
为什么算法要这么做  而不是用其他的方法
And, C is black. That's what we would have gotten
C是黑色的  我们就得到了这样的树
if we just rotated this tree, rotated B,
如果只是对树做旋转  对B旋转的话
or rotated C to the right.
或者说 把C向右旋转
So, these subtrees hang off in the same way.
这些子树还是一样挂在这儿
Subtrees look great because they all have the same black height.
子树都没问题  因为它们都有相同的黑高度
But, you see, there's a problem.
但你看 这有一个问题
If we look at all the paths starting from B
如果我们观察 所有从B出发
and going down to a leaf, on the left,
下降到的叶的路径 左边这些
the number of black nodes is
它们的黑结点数等于
whatever the black height is over here.
无论这里的黑高度是多少
Label that: black height, whereas all the paths on the right
假设它是bh  但右边所有路径
will be that black height plus one because C is black.
它们的黑高度都将是bh+1 因为C是黑色的
So now, we've violated property four.
这样就违反了性质4
So, we don't do this in case three.
所以在情形三里 我们不这样处理
After we do the rotation, we also do a recoloring.
在进行旋转后 我们还要重新上色
So, we get this. In other words,
然后 才能得到这个图 换句话说
we are putting the black node at the top
要把黑结点放在顶端
because then every path has to go through that node,
因为所有路径都会经过这个结点
whereas over here, some of the nodes went through the C.
相对于这边 有些会经过C
Some of them went through A.
有些会经过A
So, this is bad. Also, we would have violated property three.
这样不好 不仅会违反性质3
But, the really bad thing is that
但真正糟糕的是
we are violating property four over here.
这里违反了性质4
OK, let me sum up a little bit.
好的 再总结一下
So, we've seen, if we insert into a red black tree,
如果要对红黑树进行插入操作
we can keep it a red black tree.
我们可以维持其为红黑树
So, RB insert adds x to the set to the dynamic set that
RB插入：将x加入到动态集里
we are trying to maintain, and preserves red blackness.
但同时维持 并保留其红黑性
So, it keeps the tree a red black tree,
它保持了这棵树仍为红黑树
which is good because we know then it keeps logarithmic height.
这是有益的 因为它能保持树高为对数级
Therefore, all queries in red black trees
因此 红黑树里所有的查询
will keep taking logarithmic time.
都将花费对数级的时间
How long does red black insert take?
RB插入要花多长时间？
We know we are aiming for log n time preparation.
我们的目标是只花log n的准备时间
We are not going to prove that formally,
我不打算正式地证明它
but it should be pretty intuitive.
它应该很直观了
So, cases two and three, sorry, pointing at the wrong place,
情形二和情形三 不好意思 指错地方了
cases two and three are terminal.
情形二和三是终止情形
When we do case three, we are done.
当进入情形三时 就表明要结束了
When we do case two, we are about to do case three,
当进入情形二时 就意味着要进入情形三了
and then we are done.
然后就完成了
OK, so the only thing we really have to count is case one
所以唯一要计算的是情形一
because each of these operations,
因为这里的每一个操作
they are recoloring, rotation, they all take constant time.
包括重新上色、旋转  都花费常数级时间
So, it's a matter of, how many are there?
所以问题是 情形一有多少次循环？
Case one does some recoloring, doesn't change the tree at all,
情形一进行重新着色 并不改变树的结构
and moves x up by two levels.
每次x都会上移两层
We know that the height of the tree is,
因为树高已知
at most, two log n plus one.
最多是2log(n+1)
So, the number of case ones is, at most, log n plus one.
所以情形一的次数最多为log(n+1)
OK, so the number of case ones is, at most, log n.
所以 情形一的循环次数最多为log n
So, those take log n time.
所以花费log n的时间
And then, the number of case twos and threes is,
然后是情形二和情形三
at most, one for one of these columns.
每种情形最多为1遍循环
Well, together, twos and threes is, at most, two.
情形二加上情形三一起 最多为2
OK, so, log n time, cool.
所以总共是log n时间 帅气！
The other thing that is interesting about red black insertion
RB插入的另一个有意思的地方是
is that it only makes order one rotations.
它只需做O(1)次旋转
So, most of the changes are recolorings.
所以大部分改动 都是重新上色
Case one just does recoloring, no rotations.
情形一只进行重新上色 没有旋转
Case two maybe does one rotation.
情形二可能只做一次旋转
Case three does one rotation if you happen to be in those cases.
情形三也只做一次旋转 如果刚好遇到那些情况
So, the number of rotations is, at most, two.
所以旋转次数最多为2
It's either one or two in an insertion.
在一次插入里 不是1就是2
It's kind of nice because rotating a tree
这很方便 因为旋转树
is a bit more annoying than recoloring a tree.
比重新上色更加麻烦
Why? Because if you had, say, a data structure,
为什么？因为如果你有一个数据结构
you have a search tree, presumably,
假设是一个搜索树
people are using the search tree for something.
人们会拿来做一些事
They are, like, making queries.
例如查询
For example, the search tree represents all the documents
举个例子  这棵搜索树里存的是
matching the word "computer" in Google.
Google公司里 和"电脑"相关的文件
You've got the Google T-shirt on here,
因为这里有人穿了件Google的T恤
so let's use a Google reference.
所以帮Google卖个广告
You have the search tree.
这个搜索树
It stores all the things containing the word Google.
存放了所有包含有“谷歌”这个单词的文件
You'd like to search may be for the ones
你想要搜索...比如
that were modified after a certain date,
在某段时间修改过的文件
or whatever it is you want to do.
或者其它你想要的数据
So, you're doing some queries on this tree.
你要对这棵树做一些查询
And, people are pummeling Google like crazy with queries.
在查询时 人们疯狂地输入“Google”
They get a zillion a second. Don't quote me on that.
在一秒内输入无数次 不要问我怎么数的
The number may not be accurate. It's a zillion.
数量可能不精确  是不计其数的
But, people are making searches all the time.
但人们一直都在搜索
If you recolor the tree, people can still make searches.
如果对树进行重新上色 人们仍然可以搜索
It's just a little bit you are flipping.
这并不影响使用
I don't care in a search whether a node is red or black
在搜索时 我根本不会注意一个结点是红是黑
because I know it will have logarithmic height.
因为我知道它的高度是对数级就行了
So, you can come along and make your occasional updates
那么 你就可以不断地做些更新
as your crawler surfs the Web and finds changes.
一边上网玩 一边做一些改动
And, recoloring is great. Rotation is a bit expensive
重新上色没有影响  但旋转会费一些工夫
because you have to lock those nodes,
因为你必须锁定一些结点
make sure no one touches them for the duration
保证在旋转过程中
that you rotate them, and then unlock them.
没有改变它们 然后再解锁
So, it's nice that the number of rotations is small,
所以 旋转的次数越少越好
really small, just two,
真的很小 只有2
whereas the time has to be log n
尽管时间还是要log n
because we are inserting into a sorted list essentially.
因为本质上 这是给排序表做插入
So, there is an n log n lower bound if we do n insertions.
所以 如果有n个插入 时间下界是n log n
OK, deletion and I'm not going to cover here.
还有删除操作 在这里不打算讲解
You should read it in the book.
你们课后要看下书
It's a little bit more complicated, but the same ideas.
稍微复杂一点 但思路是一样的
It gets the same bounds: log n time order one rotations.
得到的界限是一样的  log n的运行时间和O(1)的旋转
So, check it out. That's red black trees.
回去看一下  这就是红黑树
Now, you can maintain data in log n time preparation: cool.
现在你可以在log n的期望时间内维护数据了  爽歪了
We'll now see three ways to do it.
我们现在已经学会了三种方法了